Guide to the Lewis Perry Curtis Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Lewis Perry Curtis family papers
1739-1980
MS 587
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
18.5
(44 boxes, 2 folios)
The papers consist of four series of professional and family material. Series I (1912-1976) contains professional correspondence and research materials of Lewis Perry Curtis. Series II contains Curtis family correspondence (1912-1976). Series III holds the correspondence of the Sullivan family (1916-1980). Material in Series IV consists of correspondence (1797-1914) and personal papers of several generations of family members, and business papers (1793-1914). The addition, Accession 1997-M-063, consists of photostatic copies of autograph letters and miscellaneous family letters (ca. 1739-1765) of Laurence Sterne and the "Continuation of the Bramine's Journal."
Curtis, Lewis Perry, 1900-1976
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Jeanet Sullivan Curtis in 1981 and Lewis Perry Curtis and Alice Curtis Desmond in 1964; and transfer from Beinecke Library, 1996.
Arrangement
Arranged in four series and one addition: I. L. P. Curtis Professional. II. L. P. Curtis Family. III. Sullivan Family. IV. Early Curtis Papers.
Scope and Contents
The Lewis Perry Curtis Family Papers, Manuscript Group Number 587, focus on the Curtis, Sullivan, and related families of Connecticut and New York. The collection is housed in forty-five boxes and is arranged in four series. The bulk of the twentieth century papers were donated to Yale University in 1981 by Jeanet (Sullivan) Curtis, while most of the nineteenth century papers were given by Lewis Perry Curtis and Alice (Curtis) Desmond in 1964. Three separate collections have been combined to form the Lewis Perry Curtis Family Papers. The Lewis Curtis Family Papers, Mss. Group No. 158, which was devoted to the nineteenth century branch of the family; the Lewis Perry Curtis Papers, Mss. Group No. 587, which contained research materials donated to Yale University by Professor Curtis; and the twentieth century papers donated by Jeanet (Sullivan) Curtis are all gathered together into this single collection of papers.
Series I, L.P. CURTIS PROFESSIONAL, thirteen boxes, contains the professional papers of Lewis Perry Curtis, the focal point of this collection. Lewis Perry Curtis, B.A. Yale 1923 and Ph.D. Yale 1926, taught in the English; History, the Arts and Letters; and History Departments at Yale University. He was an Instructor in English 1927-1931; Instructor in History, the Arts and Letters 1933-1936; Instructor in History 1936-1938; Assistant Professor of History 1938-44; Associate Professor 1944-1967; and was made Colgate Professor of History in 1967. Curtis was Paskus Fellow 1934-1938 and 1941-1945; Director of the History, the Arts and Letters program 1956-1961; editor of the Yale Historical Publications series 1947-1954; and Fellow of Jonathan Edwards College from 1933 until his death in 1976. He retired in 1969. Curtis was recognized as an expert on English history, especially conservative thought and the governing classes, and was the leading authority on Laurence Sterne. His original field was English Literature. His 1926 dissertation The Letters of Laurence Sterne formed the foundation for The Politicks of Laurence Sterne (1929). Among his other noteworthy publications were an edited work Letters of Laurence Sterne (1935), Chichester Towers (1966), and Anglican Moods in the Eighteenth Century (1966). He married Jeanet Ellinwood Sullivan in 1929.
Series I includes correspondence and other professional papers and is divided into two sections, Correspondence and Other Papers. Correspondence contains all letters written to Lewis Perry Curtis from professional colleagues, students, and friends, plus a small number of Curtis' own letters. The correspondence is arranged alphabetically by surname of correspondent and, thereafter, is arranged chronologically. Correspondence is contained in boxes 1 - 11, folders 1-356.
It is unfortunate that Series I contains so few of Curtis' own letters, for he was regarded as an excellent writer of letters. One correspondent, Davis Given, wrote on January 19, 1945 that Curtis' "letters are superb creations," and Sherman Kent in 1932 called him "the Dean of my correspondents." In several of the available letters, Lewis Perry Curtis discusses international relations and American politics. He composed an untitled poem in 1960 whose first lines are, "Let's sing a brief threnody, of Nixon and Kennedy." In other letters he writes about his distaste for "the scientific approach to history," the problems facing American education, and the tragic death of President Kennedy. Perhaps because of the death of son Michael in a mountain climbing accident in 1957, Curtis was especially moving when writing letters of sympathy. See the letters he wrote to Margaret and James Anderson in 1964 and 1968. After the death of President A. Whitney Griswold, Lewis wrote a marvelous tribute to Mary Griswold, the president's widow. Finally, in a letter to President Kingman Brewster in December 1963, he clearly outlines his views in support of Yale College, undergraduate education, and the value of teaching faculty. He opposed the graduate school mentality which he felt placed publication on a pedestal and devalued teaching. (For additional Lewis Perry Curtis letters, see the Wallace Notestein Papers, Manuscript Group Number 544. The Notestein Papers contain ten Curtis letters.)
Curtis had several different kinds of "professional" correspondents. One important group is made up of professional colleagues from Yale and other institutions of higher learning. Students and former students comprise the second major segment of correspondents, while friends and classmates make up the third. The final significant portion of letters comes from English acquaintances.
The correspondence of professional colleagues covers several subjects, including research interests, the careers of former students, academic gossip, and career problems. Several correspondents were Laurence Sterne scholars, like Arthur H. Cash, Wilbur L. Cross, Harlan W. Hamilton, Lodewick Hartley, Paul Kaufman, and Kenneth MacLean. Some of the most interesting letters concern Curtis' career problems during the early 1930s, when his friends were working to obtain a position for him at Yale. For correspondence on Lewis Perry Curtis' difficulties together with considerable gossip on Yale and the house plan, see the letters of John M. S. Allison, Robert Chapman Bates, Joseph Tony Curtiss, William H. Dunham, Robert D. French, Edgar S. Furniss, Samuel B. Hemingway, Frederick W. Hilles, Wallace Notestein, and Richard L. Purdy. Additional information on this subject can be found in Series II, Box 14, folder 426, in a letter from Curtis to his wife dated April 14, 1933, and in the correspondence of Mary Griswold and Jeanet (Sullivan) Curtis in Series III.
Scattered widely throughout other letters are further observations on Yale and academic life. Material on the struggle to promote Lewis' lifelong friend Joseph Toy Curtiss to Associate Professor of English in 1946, for example, is found in the letters of William H. Dunham, Frederick W. Hilles, Wallace Notestein, and Charles Seymour. John H. McDill, Yale 1926, onetime instructor in English, and long time friend, in letters written in 1936 and 1963, gives his opinion of Yale presidents Seymour, Griswold and Brewster. George W. Pierson in a letter of December 4, 1964 discusses the Yale teaching tradition and the inability of Yale College to insulate itself from modern publishing standards. Those who carefully examine Series I can find a great deal of information on the history of Yale from the beginning of the 1930s to the end of the 1960s and, in addition, material on the triumphs, tragedies, and frustrations of academic life.
Other correspondents were students or former students. Some of the letters are routine, like those from students asking for letters of recommendation. Many, however, are substantive in nature. Curtis felt a great obligation towards his ex-students and in his correspondence with them asked about their lives, political views and places they visited. Ramon Alcera in a letter of April 7, 1948, for example, writes about the political situation in France. Charles Dillingham, a lieutenant in the Marine Corps, on November 18, 1945, describes his feelings during the invasion of Okinawa and his desire to go into teaching in the hope of helping America's youth. Sergeant Andrew Lossby gave his impression of life in England during the war, the French character, the admirable qualities of General Omar Bradley. He also stated that "All war correspondents (except Ernie Pyle) are inveterate liars and diplomats." Frederic Eric Ossorio, Curtis' most voluminous correspondent, wrote about his Catholic view of life, Army morale, his different platoon and company officers, the Italian situation, Austria in 1945, and the Germans. When Ossorio worked at a sugar plantation in the Philippines from 1949 to 1956, he wrote about Philippine life.
Series I also contains many letters from friends and Yale classmates, some of whom later became Yale professors. Among Curtis' many close friends were Robert Chapman Bates, Joseph Toy Curtiss, William H. Dunham, Sherman Kent, John H. McDill, Morris Tyler, and Nelson C. White. All enjoyed writing letters and much of the prose was characterized by a tone of youthful flippancy and pomposity, not uncommon at the time. Jim Bordley, Lewis' roommate at Yale for four years and later a well-known physician, wrote excellent letters. He was interested in medical history and English architecture, was a book collector, and was fascinated by the Scopes Monkey trial. In a letter of August 16, 1925, he comments on the death of William Jennings Bryan. "In his passing America has lost one of her most picturesque characters, and one of her most blatant jack-asses." Nelson C. White, the Waterford, Connecticut painter, attended Pomfret School with Lewis Perry Curtis. Among other subjects, White discusses the Pomfret experience and his paintings. Morris Tyler, Yale 1924, writes about the depression and the problems faced by Yale because of it. The letters in this group, as well as in others, cover many subjects from news of friends and discussions of one's career to comments on national and international politics.
Lewis Perry Curtis also enjoyed the friendship of a great many English men and women, a friendship based directly or indirectly on his interest in Laurence Sterne and eighteenth century British life. Some of the correspondents, like Dr. George A. Auden, T.P. Cooper, Dr. William Evelyn, Kenneth Monkmen, and Alexander. Olmsted shared Curtis' interest in Sterne. Most of the rest were originally friends of friends or were people he met in research trips to Great Britain. Some of the most interesting letters dating from the World War II period show the pluck of the British. Donald R. Cameron stated on July 8, 1940 just after the disaster in France, "but we must just say that out tails are up, that we have the best navy and Air Force going, and that we now, at last, have our coats off and our sleeves rolled up, and that by God and Lockheed, we will win this bloody business once and for all, this time." Others who write about wartime life are Norman S. Hewitt, Patrick Hewitt, Ruth Hewitt, and John Humphreys.
The Correspondence section of Series I contains the letters of a large number of people writing on a wide variety of subjects. Information can be found on the history of Yale, academic life, the views of American soldiers and other Yale men on conditions in Europe, the trials of Great Britain, and comments on events of importance in the United States. The series is also useful for the indirect portrait it gives of the character, teaching, and world view of Lewis Perry Curtis. The lives of academics at Yale and elsewhere are delineated together with views of the lifestyle, interests, and ideals of two generations of education, articulate, and career minded Yale men.
The second section of Series I Other Papers fills folders 357-392 of Boxes 11-13. Other Papers contains a copy of a 1942 exam and 1945 schedule, a questionnaire sent out by the Archbishop of York in 1764, fifteen folders of typed answers to those questions, a reel of microfilm, and eighteen folders of photostats of the papers of Robert Hay Drummond(1711-1776), Archbishop of York 1771-1776. These folders have research material that Curtis used in studying eighteenth century British life.
Series II L. P. CURTIS FAMILY fills Boxes 14-17, folders 393-534. It primarily contains correspondence, but also includes some other papers. Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by correspondent and then chronologically. Papers relating to several members of the Curtis family, for example, report cards for the children at Foote School in New Haven, are found after the letters of that person, while miscellaneous papers are located at the and of the series in folders 525-534.
L. P. CURTIS FAMILY houses letters addressed to Lewis Perry Curtis by relatives, including Sullivan in-laws, and also a small number of letters written to other members of the Curtis family. See the Family Charts following this introduction and a Curtis genealogical chart in Box 17, folder 532, for a delineation of family relationships. These charts list most, but not all, of the family correspondents. Those not included fall into one of three categories. First, a handful of correspondents are unlisted because they belong to a later generation than those found on the charts. Italian cousins Edmondo Ruspoli and Beatrice Miani fall into this group. Others like Henry A. Schroeder, Bertha Leake, Katherine (Perry) Shaw, and Charlotte Perry are too distantly related to be listed. Henry A. Schroeder, for example, was a second cousin, the grandson of a sister of Mary (Hughes) Wells, the grandmother of Lewis Perry Curtis. Amy (Johnson) Bates, Amy Groesbeck, and Abby E. Ellsworth can best be characterized as honorary relatives. Amy Bates was the mother of Robert C. Bates and Amy Groesbeck was his half-sister. Abby E. Ellsworth was the mother of Joseph Toy Curtiss.
One subject about which there is information in some detail is the Depression. Lewis Beers Curtis, Lewis' uncle, was extremely wealthy and the Sullivans were also affluent, but Lewis' brother Edward Livingston Wells Curtis of Southport, Connecticut was not so fortunate. Wells Curtis lost his real estate position during the Depression and like many other previously secure middle class Americans had to face unemployment and the possibility of losing everything. "Here we are," he stated on September 20, 1932, "Bess and I, fairly able bodied adults with fair educations, ready and willing to do anything to bring in some of the necessary wherewithall, and from month to month nothing happens. Our home is gone and we are objects of charity." Several letters from Wells Curtis and Lousia (Wells) Curtis discuss his difficulties and those faced by others in a similar predicament. Some Southport relatives, however, like sister Louise(Curtis)Roche and Katherine (Perry) Shaw blithely ignored the Depression and continued their normal social activities.
As one might expect, much of the correspondence in L. P. CURTIS FAMILY concerns the daily life of and news of the doings of relatives and mutual friends. Its value, therefore, is primarily for those interested in genealogy and family history. Dr. Henry A. Schroeder, as an example, in a 1964 letter mentions an hereditary disease, "progressive muscular dystrophy," passed on through the Hughes line. In letters written in 1944 and 1945, Jonathan Godfrey gives Lewis information about the French and Italian branches of the Curtis family, descended from Joseph Davis Beers Curtis. Louisa (Wells) Curtis and Louise (Curtis) Roche, Lewis' mother and sister, are the two who write most regularly and one gets the greatest family news from them. Other useful family history is scattered throughout Series II, together with information about daily life and occasional comments on the national scene.
Series III SULLIVAN FAMILY contains the correspondence and other papers of Jeanet Ellinwood (Sullivan) Curtis. It includes letters that she wrote to her family, letters directed to her by Sullivan and Curtis relatives, and the correspondence of her many friends. SULLIVAN FAMILY is found in Boxes 18-25, folders 535-786. It is arranged in the same way as Series I and II.
Jeanet (Sullivan) Curtis is the daughter of Walter Seager and Jeanet (Loomis) Sullivan. Her father was a reporter and advertising manager for The New York Times and later on officer with the Mutual Life Insurance Company of New York from 1902 to 1939. The family was prosperous, having homes on 61 East Eighteenth Street in New York City and Boontown, New Jersey. Three daughters graduated from Bryn Mawr and son Walter graduated from Yale. Jeanet's older sister Elinor married James P. Hendrick, a classmate of Lewis Perry Curtis', who became a Wall Street lawyer and government official. Younger sister Constance, called Connie, married a New York doctor, George A. Carden, Jr.Brother Walter is science editor for The New York Times and a well-known author. Nancy, the fourth sister, was an epileptic and semi-invalid. Jeanet, Elinor, and James P. Hendrick were all talented amateur musicians, while Constance (Sullivan) Carden studied voice and wished to pursue a professional singing career.
Series III contains personal and family correspondence. It includes relatively little discussion of events of national significance, although in portions of several letters, particularly those written by sister Connie and Jeanet's parents, there are comments on the Depression, the election of 1932, and Franklin Delano Roosevelt. In addition, there is some material on conditions at Yale during the early 1930s and the difficulties Lewis Perry Curtis endured before securing a position in the History, the Arts, and Letters program in 1933. The letters of Jeanet (Sullivan) Curtis and Mary Griswold are most useful in this regard, although Cecily Thompson also contributes information on the former subject in letters written in October 1932 and March 1933. The situation at Yale she wrote, "has grown perfectly impossible. Everyone is steeped in politics and there is so much talk and malicious gossip going around that you simply don't know who is your friend any more."
In addition to news of family activities, SULLIVAN FAMILY, contains many references to their musical interests, in particular preparation for concerts and the progress of Connie's studies. The Sullivans appear to have been largely unaffected by the Depression. They continued to travel throughout the United States and Europe and to enjoy the cultural opportunities offered by New York City. The correspondence of Constance (Sullivan) Carden, Jeanet (Loomis) Sullivan, and Walter Seager Sullivan is especially useful for anyone wishing to study the lifestyle of prosperous Americans during the Depression.
Jeanet's brother Walter, called Wallie, became a reporter for The New York Times after graduating from Yale in 1940. He spent several years as a foreign correspondent in the Far East and Germany, but his letters are primarily personal in character. Before and after, however, a trip to Little American in Antarctica in 1946, Wallie wrote a couple of interesting letters. The first from Balboa, Panama in December 1946 includes an Errol Flynn anecdote and the second dated March 31, 1947 describes a trip to New Zealand and includes a devastating review of a concert given by a third rate Russian violinist.
Series I-III contain correspondence and other papers relating to Lewis Perry Curtis and Jeanet (Sullivan) Curtis and each series is arranged in the same manner. Some letters contain annotations by Lewis Perry Curtis. He calls Katherine (Perry) Shaw, for example, "the most brilliant woman I have ever known" and states that William F. Buckley, Jr. was the "provocative editor of the Yale News, 1949-1950."
Series IV EARLY CURTIS PAPERS forms the largest series in the collection, filling Boxes 26-45. It has the letters and papers of several nineteenth [illegible] century ancestors of Lewis Perry Curtis, the two most important being Joseph Dewis Beers and Lewis Curtis, his great-great-grandfather and great-grandfather. The series includes correspondence, diaries, deeds, memoranda, estate books, contracts, bills and receipts, stock certificates, cancelled checks, and account books. The series is divided into two sections, Personal Papers and Business Papers. Personal Papers is contained in Boxes 26-34. Correspondence, Boxes 26-29, is followed by alphabetically arranged personal files, Boxes 30-34.
The Personal Papers section contains the letters of four generations of Curtises and related families. The related families represented include Beers, Chapman, Perry, Steele, and Wells plus additional correspondence from people who are related through the female lines of Giles, Gorham, Gregory, Hughes, Marvine, Mills and Tallyrand. Personal Papers also includes letters of acquaintances and friends. All personal correspondence, therefore, as opposed to business correspondence, and all letters to and from family members, regardless of subject matter are found in this section of Series IV.
Joseph D. Beers was born in Newtown, Connecticut, but moved as a youth to Stamford in Ulster County, later Delaware County, New York. He became a merchant in Hobart, Delaware County, New York and moved to New York City in 1815 entering into several partnerships, the best known being J.D. Beers & Co. Beers formally retired from business in 1835, but stayed active until his death twenty-eight years later, principally concerning himself with land speculation and stock investments.
Lewis Curtis was born in Stratford, Connecticut, moved to New York City in 1807 to enter the mercantile business, and later married Mary Elizabeth Beers, the only child of Joseph D. and Mary (Chapman) Beers. He enjoyed a long and successful business career, heading with his brother Benjamin L. & B. Curtis & Co., one of the largest importers of fabrics and dry goods in the country.
Both Beers and Curtis were Episcopalians and Lewis Curtis was active in several benevolent societies. He had a life membership in the New York Tract Society and served for more than forty years as a member of the Committee for Foreign Missions of the Protestant Episcopal Church, later called the Domestic and Foreign Missionary Society. The section contains several letters, mostly written during the 1830s, from prominent Episcopal churchmen, including Bishop William R. Whittingham (1805-1879), Reverend Jonathan M. Wainwright (1792-1854), Henry J. Seaman, and Bishop Thomas C. Brownell (1779-1865). Both served as bank presidents. Beers headed the North American Trust and Banking Company and Curtis was president of the Farmers Loan & Trust Co. For further information on their business careers, see the Business Papers part of Series IV.